"How to Get Enough “Lifespan Essential” Polyphenols"
Polyphenols are
among the front runners
in developing dietary approaches
to fight age-associated disease.
There is such
a critical mass of data
in favor of the protective
benefits of these
"lifespan essentials"
that recommended daily
intakes of polyphenols
have been proposed.
More than 8,000
different polyphenols
have been identified,
though only a small proportion
have had their health effects
cataloged.
Shared structural features
make them among
the most powerful dietary
antioxidants in vitro,
but in our bodies,
mechanistic effects have been
attributed to their ability
to modulate cellular signal
transduction pathways.
In the PREDIMED trial,
those in the top fifth
of polyphenol intake
had a 37 percent reduction
in all-cause mortality
compared to those in
the lower fifth of consumption,
which over an adult lifetime
could translate into
about four more years of life.
However, the high polyphenol
group was eating
nine servings of fruits
and vegetables a day
compared to the five a day eaten
by the low polyphenol group;
so, it's possible there were
other phytonutrients at play.
Coffee and tea are major
sources, but in terms of foods,
polyphenols come primarily from
vegetables, fruits, then beans.
There are about a half dozen
different types of polyphenols,
including phenolic acids
like the curcumin in turmeric
or the lignans
concentrated in flaxseeds,
but the largest class
are the flavonoids.
Plant eaters may consume
more than 4,000 different
types of flavonoids
on a daily basis.
Flavonoids include the
anthocyanin pigments in berries,
the isoflavones in soy foods,
the catechins in tea like EGCG,
the flavonones in citrus,
and the flavonols,
like quercetin and fisetin,
which people get from foods
like apples, onions,
and strawberries.
Like polyphenols generally,
those who consume
the most flavonoids
tend to live
significantly longer,
according to a meta-analysis
of 16 cohort studies
following nearly
a half million people
for 5 to 28 years.
However, those who get more
are also more likely
to be college-educated,
non-Hispanic white
with a higher income.
The sharpest
socioeconomic gradient
was found for berry flavonoids.
If you look at
individual foods, though,
as Harvard researchers did
in the Nurses' Health Study II,
it wasn't just
blueberries and strawberries
that were correlated with a
lower risk of premature death,
but also
more affordable produce,
such as apples and bell peppers.
To prove cause and effect,
researchers randomized
middle-aged men and women
to eat higher-
or lower-polyphenol diets
in the Polyphenol
Intervention Trial.
Eight weeks later,
the higher-polyphenol diet group
enjoyed significant improvements
in quality of life—
both physically and mentally—
compared to
the lower-polyphenol diet group.
But what did the two diets
consist of?
The lower-polyphenol diet group
was told to restrict
fruits and vegetables
to no more than
2 servings a day,
whereas the higher-polyphenol
group was to eat six servings
(including a portion
of berries),
plus two ounces (60 g)
of dark chocolate a day.
So, it could have been any
number of fruit and vegetable
components besides polyphenols
responsible for the benefit.
Just the enforced
chocolate consumption
might have boosted well-being!
A more rigorous study design
might be
to randomize both groups
to the same number
of high-versus-low-polyphenol
fruit and vegetable servings.
In the Nurses' Health Study,
you may have noticed that
one food source of flavonoids
was associated with an increased
risk of all-cause mortality:
grapefruit.
Frequent grapefruit consumers
were more likely
to die prematurely
than their non-grapefruit-eating
compatriots
matched for a large number
of demographic
and lifestyle factors.
This was partly chalked up
to grapefruit's suppression
of a set of detoxification
enzymes in our intestines
that may metabolize half
the common drugs on the market.
Broccoli has
the opposite effect,
boosting detox enzymes
such that some drugs
can be cleared faster,
whereas even a single cup
(240 ml) of grapefruit juice
can reduce the rate
of drug clearance for days,
increasing the risk
of potentially life-threatening
drug side effects.
That's why grapefruit
has been called
a "pharmacologist's nightmare."
If you're on medications
(including many common heart
and blood pressure pills)
make sure to talk
to your prescriber
about your grapefruit habits.